好吧，让我们开始吧，欢迎回来，这是第十二个
okay let's get started
welcome back it's the this is the 12th
浓缩物课程的讲座你好，还是星期一，所以当我们离开时
lecture of the condensed matter course
hello is it Monday still so when we left
我们谈论的是散射标准散射实验
off we were talking about scattering the
standard scattering experiment did you
有一些样本在波矢K处发送一些波，然后出现一些东西
have some sample you send in some wave
at wave vector K and something comes out
和波向量K Prime并通过测量在各种波向量K处产生的结果
and wave vector K Prime and by measuring
what comes out at various wave vectors K
首要的，我们应该能够从微观上推断出结构
Prime we're supposed to be able to
deduce the structure the microscopic
样本的结构，我想再次强调一下，
structure of the sample and I want to
emphasize again that this type of
实验是理解事物微观结构的方式
experiment is the way to understand the
microscopic structures of things on
规模小于您实际能看到的诺贝尔奖数量
scales smaller than you can actually see
with your eye the number of Nobel Prizes
进行此类实验的人获得的奖励是巨大的
that have been awarded for people doing
this type of experiment is enormous
大概有20 25 30个无知的奖品
there's like 20 25 30 ignoble prizes
just a couple of famous ones you know
牛津大学的多萝西·霍奇金·萨默维尔最喜欢的女儿赢得了
Oxford's own Dorothy Hodgkin
Somerville's favorite daughter won a
发现青霉素和胰岛素的结构获得诺贝尔奖
Nobel Prize for discovering the
structure of penicillin and insulin
使用X射线散射，沃森和克里克（Watson and Crick）非常著名地发现了DNA的两倍
using x-ray scattering Watson and Crick
very famously figured out the DNA double
他们通过查看X射线散射数据得出的螺旋结构
helix structure which they figured out
by looking at x-ray scattering data
罗莎琳德·富兰克林（Rosalind Franklin）摄Russell Franklin不幸去世，
taken by rosalind Franklin Russell
Franklin sadly died extremely young and
因此，她被剥夺了诺贝尔奖以及她的余生
was therefore denied a Nobel Prize as
well as the rest of her life just very
伤心，但每个人都应该知道她的名字
sad but everyone should know her name
nonetheless anyway this is an extremely
重要的实验，这就是为什么我们要花很多时间在
important experiment and that's why
we're spending so much time on it at
至少是本讲座的下一个讲座，也许是之后的一些讲座
least this lecture next lecture and
maybe some of the lecture there after
我们在上一堂课中得出的一件事是，为了获得
one of the things we derived in the last
lecture is that in order to get
从k到k素数的散射，我们必须在晶体中满足老挝条件
scattering from k to k prime we must
satisfy in a crystal the lao e condition
K减去K素数现在必须是倒数晶格向量G
that K minus K prime must be a
reciprocal lattice vector G now at the
在上一堂课结束时，我声称这种情况很糟糕
very end of last lecture I claimed that
this condition this lousy condition is
与您在考虑时已经考虑过的情况非常相似
very similar to a condition that you
have already thought about when you
被认为只是平面上的简单衍射，您拥有光或X射线，或者
considered just simple diffraction off
of planes you have light or x-rays or
进入一组平行平面的东西或中子
something or neutrons coming into a set
of parallel planes a family of lattice
平面和您有不同，我们了解如何获得衍射
planes and you have different you we
understand how you can get diffraction
这种类型与平行的
of this sort at
certain angles off of parallel family of
飞机，我要说这种情况实际上是
planes and I'm gonna claim that this
this condition here is actually
等价于此，所以我们首先要做的是回顾一些
equivalent to that so first what we're
gonna do is we're going to review some
关于平面衍射的事情，那么我们将证明糟糕的是
things about diffraction off of planes
then we're gonna show that the lousy
条件和衍射条件是相同的，所以让我们抽象一下
condition and the diffraction conditions
are the same so let's uh abstract this
像这样在一组飞机上拍一些照片，想像一下我们
picture a little bit to just a set of
planes like this and well imagine we
像这样有波进来，它像这样以角度θ反射
have some wave coming in like this it
reflects off like this at an angle theta
而且还有另外一个平行波像这样完全一样的波
but also another parallel wave coming in
like this exactly the same wave just
下降到一层，像这样以相同的角度θ进一步衍射
goes down to one layer further diffract
off like this the same angle theta like
这个，我要去强调，我也许可以
this and I'm just going I'm going to
actually emphasize this I may be able to
甚至将其写下来，因为它是错误总数的极为常见的来源
even write it down because it's an
extremely common source of error total
偏转角偏转角等于theta为什么为什么有theta
deflection angle deflection angle equals
to theta why is that well there's theta
那里还有另一个θ，所以角度差
there and another theta there so the
difference the difference in angle
传入波和传出波之间实际上是两个theta
between the incoming wave and the
outcoming wave is actually two theta you
知道这会给很多人带来各种各样的悲伤，所以请确保
know that this this causes all sorts of
grief to a lot of people so make sure
你知道什么时候你在谈论theta以及你在谈论两个theta
you know when you're talking about theta
and what are you talking about two theta
因此，当您在前几年进行这种类型的计算时，您知道
so as you did this this type of
calculation in prior years you know that
您需要做的是计算额外距离
the what you need to do is you need to
calculate the additional distance
由第二波传播，所以如果我在此处垂直放置
traveled by the second wave so if I drop
a perpendicular here and a perpendicular
如果D是两者之间的距离，则此处的附加距离为d正弦角
here the additional distance here is d
sine theta if D is the distance between
因此，为了获得相长干涉
the the layers so in order to get
constructive interference constructive
哦，也许我先写这个额外距离
oh maybe maybe I'll write this first the
additional distance additional distance
距离等于2 D正弦theta等于2 D正弦theta所以它是D正弦theta
distance is then 2 D sine theta equals 2
D sine theta so it's D sine theta on
在这边，然后在那边再有一个D正弦θ，因此额外的距离
this side and then another D sine theta
on that side so the additional distance
由第二平面反射回来的波所取的是2 D正弦θ2
taken by the by the wave that reflected
off the second plane is 2 D sine theta 2
建设性干涉建设性干涉
constructive interference constructive
干扰罐子的放屁我想这是我在写作中所说的
interference in jar farrance I think
it's as the term goes on my writing gets
更糟的是，我们得到的是n lambda等于两个正弦θ，因此您必须有一个整数
worse we get is n lambda equals two sine
theta so you have to have an integer
该额外距离中包含的波长数量看起来是否全部
number of wavelengths contained in that
extra distance does that all look
前几年很熟悉，是的，所以我要在它周围放一个盒子，因为它
familiar from previous years yeah okay
so I'll put a box around it because it's
一个重要的方程式称为布拉格条件布拉格条件
an important equation this is known as
the Bragg condition Bragg condition
继威廉·亨利和威廉·劳伦斯·布拉格父子团队之后
after William Henry and William Lawrence
Bragg the father-and-son team who
开创性的X射线散射William Lawrence Bragg在2006年获得了诺贝尔奖
pioneered x-ray scattering William
Lawrence Bragg winning a Nobel Prize at
25岁的他对巧克力棒的X射线散射所做的工作
the age of 25 for his work on x-ray
scattering for a chocolate bar does
谁知道第二个最年轻的诺贝尔奖获得者是谁
anyone know who the second youngest
Nobel laureate was it's a name you all
知道这些都是真的很好的猜测，但是这些都是错误的，真的很接近
know those are all really good guesses
but those are all wrong really close to
他们都是同一个时代的海森堡，他们在那里说了哦，我的天哪足够近了，是的
all of them same era Heisenberg who said
it up there oh my gosh close enough yes
海森堡恰好是狄拉克（Dirac），当时年纪才几个月
Heisenberg exactly Dirac was just a few
months older well then then then
海森堡好吧，所以现在我向你宣称是这种情况
Heisenberg all right so now that when I
claim to you was that this condition
这种布拉德条件很活跃，却忘记了建设性干扰
this Brad condition is active forgetting
constructive interference
您只会从某些角度产生建设性干扰
you only get constructive interference
coming off on certain angles from your
水晶，那个状况实际上和这个糟糕的状况相同
crystal that that condition is actually
the same condition as this lousy
罐子的状况就是晶体动量的守恒
condition over here the can which is the
conservation of crystal momentum so
让我们看看是否可以证明将其写下来，因为这是等价的
let's see if we can prove that write
this down because this is a equivalence
布拉格抹布和哇哇好吧，同样的图，我们在一个家庭中有两个平行的平面
bragg rag and wowie okay so same diagram
we have two parallel planes in a family
晶格平面，您实际上可以有点理解为什么
of lattice plane you can actually you
can kind of understand why it is that
这两个将是相关的，请记住上一堂课
these two are going to be related
remember from last lecture that
倒易的晶格矢量与晶格族相关
reciprocal lattice vectors are
associated with families of lattice
飞机，所以gee会告诉你
planes so
gee up there is going to be telling you
关于这个晶格平面族的一些事实，我们拥有的事实
something about this family of lattice
planes so the the fact that we have
平行平面是因为我们有一个倒数的晶格矢量
parallel planes is because we have a
reciprocal lattice vector those are sort
等价语句的集合，所以在这里我们将晶格平面族分开
of equivalent statements so here we have
our family of lattice planes separated
在一定距离D处，我们在波矢K处有一个入射波，并将其传出
by some distance D we have an incoming
wave at wave vector K and outgoing it
波向量K素，然后由于我们那里有一个晶格平面族
wave vector K Prime that and then since
we have a family of lattice planes there
是正交向量G，它是一个倒数的晶格向量
is a orthogonal vector G which is a
reciprocal lattice vector that was one
上一次衍生出来的东西，然后每次我们有一个家庭
of the things we derive last time then
every time we have a family of lavs
平面上有一个与其垂直的倒数晶格矢量，因为我们有
planes there's a reciprocal lattice
vector perpendicular to it since we have
因为我们有弹性散射K的大小和K的大小
since we have elastic scattering the
magnitude of K and the magnitude of K
质数是相同的，实际上定义了一些单位向量
Prime are the same and that's actually
define some unit vectors unit vectors of
XK帽子K素色帽子和G帽子要适当的指向
X K hat K prime hat and G hat to be
pointing in the the appropriate
方向，然后有一点点几何形状K hat dot G hat equals正弦
directions and then with a little bit of
geometry K hat dot G hat equals sine
theta只需花一秒钟，确保您确信如果k hat和g
theta just take a second make sure
you're convinced of that if k hat and g
帽子指向同一方向，那么混乱的帽子将为1正弦θ
hat were pointing in the same direction
then chaotic g hat would be 1 sine theta
在那种情况下也将是1而相反的K素数帽子
would also be 1 in that case whereas K
prime hat which is going in the opposite
方向G帽子是正弦减theta好的，我们也可以使用我们将需要的
direction G hat is minus sine theta okay
and we can also use we're gonna need
我们可以将K向量写为K的大小，即Lambda上的2 PI
that that K vector we can write as the
magnitude of K which is 2 PI over lambda
λ波长乘以K
with lambda the wave vector with the
wavelength times K hat everyone happy
到目前为止，是的，很好，所以我们要假设处于低矮状态
with this so far yeah ok good so we're
gonna assume the lowry condition so
假设毛伊等于K减去K素数等于G，所以假设满足并且我
assume maui that is K minus K prime
equals G so assume that satisfied and I
可以重写为λ2乘以λ乘以K
can rewrite that then as 2 PI over
lambda times K hat minus K prime hat
等于G，然后用G帽子加点，以在λG帽子上得到2个PI。
equals G then dot with G hat to get 2 PI
over lambda G hat dot k hat minus G hat
点k素数帽子等于G帽子点G向量好，那么我们将替换为
dot k prime hat equals G hat dot G
vector okay then we'll substitute in we
只是G帽子的点k帽子是正弦θ，所以我们将其替换为
just had the G hat dot k hat is sine
theta so we'll substitute that in so we
在lambda上获得2 PI，所以这是正弦θ在这里第二项是负正弦
get 2 PI over lambda so this is sine
theta here the second term is minus sine
theta然后G hat G vector就是G vector的绝对值
theta and then G hat G vector is just
the absolute value of G vector
每个人都还开心，好吧，不，不开心，是啊，仍然开心，嗯，好，所以
everyone's still happy ok um no not
happy yeah still happy um okay so just a
一点点重排，这在绝对G向量乘以2正弦时变成2 PI
little bit of rearrangement this becomes
2 PI over absolute G vector times 2 sine
theta等于lambda，现在记住我们说的是上次导出的内容
theta equals lambda and now remember
what we said what we derived last time
关于互易的晶格矢量晶格平面D之间的间距为2 PI
about reciprocal lattice vectors the
spacing between lattice planes D is 2 PI
在给定方向G min上最短的倒数晶格矢量上
over the shortest reciprocal lattice
vector in a given direction G min so any
倒数晶格向量G向量必须是最小值的整数倍
reciprocal lattice vector G vector has
to be some integer times the minimum
在给定方向上的晶格矢量，所以n是一些整数，所以
lattice vector in that given direction
so n is some integer integer so
将此等式中的等式代入上面的等式
substituting this equation in this
equation into the equation just above
给我们2个D正弦theta等于和lambda布拉格条件，所以我们已经
gives us 2 D sine theta equals and
lambda the Bragg condition so what we've
结果表明，在低e条件下，晶体动量守恒是
shown is that the low e condition this
conservation of crystal momentum is the
与需要建设性干涉或拥有布拉格一样
same thing as requiring constructive
interference or having the Bragg
条件满意还可以吧
condition satisfied ok good
all right so
假设我们有布拉格条件或优等条件
supposing that we have the Bragg
condition or the laude condition
我们上次得出的结论之一是
satisfied one of the things we derive
last time was that the intensity of
散射强度与结构强度成正比
scattering intensity of scattering is
proportional to the structure factor at
GK减去K素数平方，结构因子s等于
G K minus K prime squared the structure
factor s equals the Fourier transform of
EMR的散射潜能听起来像上一堂课一样
the scattering potential of EMR does
that sound familiar from last lecture I
希望还可以，但是问题仍然存在。
hope ok but that still leaves up in the
question what is V of R and what V of R
波进入晶体时感觉到的潜力取决于
is what the potential your wave feels as
it goes into the crystal depends on well
取决于晶体，但也取决于您是哪种波
depends on the crystal but it also
depends on what kind of wave you're
使用您知道波与晶体的相互作用非常不同，取决于
using you know the wave interacts with
the crystal very differently depending
根据您使用的波形类型，因此更容易考虑的情况是
on the type of wave that you're using so
the easier case to think about is
中子所以案例1中子中子
neutrons so case 1 neutrons neutrons
主要通过短程近程通过核力进行相互作用
interact mainly mainly via nuclear
forces by a short-range short-range
核力量和核力量
nuclear forces and nuclear forces
那么这意味着中子进入了样本，他们看到了
so what does that mean it means the
neutrons go into the sample and they see
与原子核相关的非常短程的电势，我们可以写出V
very short-range potentials associated
with the nuclei and we can write the V
R等于或正比于我猜所有原子的原子之和
of R equals or it's proportional to I
guess sum over atoms from all atoms
整个系统中的alpha系数为alpha乘以delta
alpha in the whole system some
coefficient be alpha times a delta
R减去R alpha的功能势，所以基本上说每个原子核
function potential at R minus R alpha so
basically saying that every nucleus so
我们的alpha是原子alpha的位置，而alpha是在
our alpha is position of atom alpha
position of alpha and be alpha is in the
与该原子核相互作用的大小被称为核子
the magnitude of the interaction with
that nucleus it's known as the nuclear
散射长度散射长度，所以这个方程的本质是
scattering length scattering length and
so the essence of this equation is
基本上说，进入它们的中子看到了非常尖锐的峰值
basically saying that the the neutrons
coming in they see very sharp peaks in
在核位置的潜力，这就是他们所没有看到的
potential at the positions of the nuclei
and and that's all they don't see
现在其他任何这些系数，因为它们必须
anything else
now these coefficients be they have to
核物理学和核物理学可能非常复杂
do with nuclear physics and nuclear
physics can be extremely complicated
根据具体情况，它们可以是正数或负数
they can be positive or they can be
negative depending on the particular
我们所说的正核意味着您具有排斥性相互作用
nucleus we're talking about positive
means you have a repulsive interaction
负核意味着您与
with the nucleus negative means you have
an attractive interaction with the
核，你也可以任一个，这些蜜蜂的大小可以变化，你知道
nucleus and you can either either and
the size of these bees can vary you know
取决于您正在考虑的特定原子核
by it Lots depending on the particular
nucleus you're thinking about and really
知道B对于特定原子核的唯一方法是只查找它
the only way to know what B is for a
particular nucleus is to just look it up
在桌子上或测量它，您知道周期中可能有两个原子
on a table or measure it you know you
could have two atoms on the periodic
彼此相邻的桌子，例如碳氮和核
table that are right next to each other
like carbon nitrogen and the nuclear
散射长度是完全不同的，你知道有些可以是正的
scattering lengths is completely
different you know some can be positive
有些可能是负面的，它到处都是，所以实际上是
some can be negative it just goes all
over the place so it's actually a
我们甚至无法真正预测核物理学家的东西
something that we can't actually predict
very easily even nuclear physicist even
好的核物理学家很难预测这些事情，所以我们只有
good nuclear physicists have a hard time
predicting these things so we just have
你知道诉诸表，并假设这些东西是已知的
to you know resort to a table and assume
that these things are known or this
以某种方式我们将能够测量它们，但是给定
somehow we're going to be able to
measure them but given
我们具有这种与核相互作用的功能形式
that we have this sort of functional
form of the interaction with the nuclei
然后我们可以计算G的结构因子s
we can then calculate the structure
factor structure factor s of G which
记住定义是它实际上是dpr这是权威
remember the definition is that it's
actually dpr it's the authority
在单位单元中将e的单位单元中的傅立叶变换为I
transform in the unit cell the fourier
transform in the unit cell of e to the I
G点R乘以R的V
G dot R times V of R something we
derived last time and if we actually
插入上面刚刚记下的表格，我们得出的总和超过了alpha
plug in the the form that we just wrote
down above we have sum over alpha be
Alpha Delta 3维Delta函数R减去R sub alpha现在我们将
Alpha Delta 3 dimensional Delta function
R minus R sub alpha now we'll let the
Delta函数的作用，我们得到了相当简单的结果并总结了Adams
Delta function act and we get the fairly
simple outcome and to sum over Adams
V sub alpha e到IG点R sub alpha的晶胞中的alpha Adams alpha，其中
alpha Adams alpha in unit cell of V sub
alpha e to the I G dot R sub alpha where
R sub alpha是原子alpha在晶胞alpha中的位置，因此
R sub alpha is the position of position
of atom alpha in unit cell alpha so
在那里，所以这是散射
there we have it so that's the structure
factor for scattering scattering of
现在中子对原子核是超级中子
neutrons against nuclei now that's for
super neutrons neutrons being fairly
很简单，但还有第二种情况，我们需要担心的是x射线和
simple but there's a second case that we
need to worry about which is x rays and
X射线是更复杂的麦克射线X射线是电磁X射线
x-rays are more complicated mike rays x
rays well their electromagnetism x-rays
你知道吗，像光一样，它们主要散射，主要是电子散射
are you know like light they mainly
scatter mainly scatter from electrons
电子通过汤姆森从电子中散射
scatter from electrons from from
electrons electrons via Thomson
他去年研究了汤姆森散射，所以听起来很熟悉
scattering he studies Thomson scattering
last year so it sound familiar yeah so
他们通过汤普森散射从电子中散射出来，有一点点
they made a scattering from electrons
via Thompson scattering there's a little
汤姆森散布在原子核上，但实际上非常非常小
bit of Thomson scattering off the nuclei
but really very very very small amount
因为与电子相比，原子核非常重，所以它们
because the the nuclei are very heavy
compared to the electrons and so they're
很难散开，很难推开它们
very hard to scatter off of it's hard to
push them around
推电子很容易，因为它们很轻，所以主要是我们的V
it's easy to push the electrons around
because they're light so mainly V of our
对于我们的X射线，有效相互作用与密度成正比
for our x-rays the effective interaction
is proportional to the density of
电子的电子密度，那么我们能得到的电子密度是多少
electrons density of electrons so what's
the density of electrons well we can
写出电子密度的近似表达式
write sort of an approximate expression
for the density of electrons which will
在原子αZ子alpha Z上写一些总和，这里是原子数
write as some sum over atoms alpha Z sub
alpha Z here being the atomic number
原子的原子序数alpha原子序数是其中的电子数
atomic number of atom alpha atomic
number being the number of electrons in
原子中的质子数也乘以某些函数
the in the atom also the number of
protons in the atom times some function
我称R的G sub alpha减去R alpha，我想我们可以这样称呼
I'll call G sub alpha of R minus R alpha
which I guess we can call something like
归一化的形状函数，因此其积分为1，我们可以进行比较
a shape function which is normalized so
it's integral is 1 and we can compare
与我们这里所看到的相似，除了这里是一个三角洲
that to what we have over here looks
kind of similar except here it's a delta
函数，这里不是增量函数，所以区别是
function and here it's not a delta
function so the the difference being
当您是中子时，您只会从核中飞散
that when you if you're a neutron you
you scatter off of only the nucleus
而如果您是X射线，则您会散射整个原子，因此您可以
whereas if you're an x-ray you scatter
off of the whole atom so you can kind of
认为这个G是一个非常非常胖的Delta函数，它散布开来
think of this G as being a very very fat
Delta function it's spread out spreading
将Delta函数转换为某些函数，您知道它只需要
out the Delta function into some
function there's you know it just takes
考虑到原子中所有电子的整体大小，因此将其视为
into account the entire size of all the
electrons in the atom so think of it as
一种原子，所以现在我应该说，这种形式
a sort of atom so now I should say
however that this this form where we're
总结所有这些不同原子的形状乘以
summing up over the shapes of all these
different atoms times the number of
每个原子中的电子有点近似，原因是
electrons in each atom is a little bit
approximate and the reason it's a little
有点近似是因为这里有一个隐含的假设
bit approximate is because there's an
assumption the hidden assumption here
如果原子的形状独立于其环境
that the shape of the atom is
independent of its environment if an
原子碰巧与一种特定类型的原子结合，实际上
atom happens to be bonded to an one
particular type of atom it will actually
稍微扭曲原子的电子云，因此形状将改变
distort the electron cloud of the atom a
little bit so the shape will change a
一点，我们已经忽略了它，如果它键合到另一种原子上
little bit and we've ignored that and if
it's bonded to a different type of atom
它的形状会在另一个方向上发生一些变化
its shape will will change a little bit
in maybe another direction it will
取决于粘合方向，依此类推，依此类推
depend on which direction it's bonded
and so forth and so on
但是-这是一个非常好的第一近似
but
- a very good first approximation this
是描述任何电子密度的形状的一种很好的方法
is a fairly good way to describe the the
shape of the density of electrons in any
水晶，只要您知道自己具有特定类型的原子的形状，
crystal just you know you have a shape
of for a particular type of atom and you
将其加到所有原子上，而忽略相邻原子将
add it up over all atoms and you ignore
the fact that neighboring atoms will
扭曲形状好吧好吧，所以我们可以采用这种形式的
distort the shape okay good all right
so we can take this form of the of the
电子密度并再次构造G的结构因子s
density of electrons and again construct
the structure factor s of G which is now
所有原子的总和D 3的alpha积分与我们所做的非常相似
sum over all atoms atoms alpha integral
of D 3 are very similar to what we did
就在单位晶格上方，然后我们有e到IJ点R，有z
just over here over the unit cell then
we have e to the I J dot R we have z
sub-alpha，如果我们为您进行转换，我们有R-R alpha的G sub alpha
sub-alpha and we have G sub alpha of R -
R alpha if we do that for you transform
我们得到的东西与我们在这里得到的东西非常相似
what we get is extremely similar to what
we get over here very similar to this
在这里，我们得到的方程式是亚当斯α和
equation here what we get is of the
following form sum over adams alpha and
e到IG点RF子alpha的e单位单元格，请使用其他字母作为
unit cell of e to the I G dot R F sub
alpha you use different letter as a
G的函数这称为原子形状因数
function of G this is known as the
atomic form factor form factor it
取决于我们正在谈论的原子类型以及您是否想知道
depends on the type of atom we're
talking about and if you want to know
原子形状因数实际上是什么，所以实际上可以将其与
what the atomic form factor actually is
so actually maybe just compare it to
在这里，原子形状因子代替了核散射
over here the atomic form factor takes
the place of the nuclear scattering
此处的长度代替了B alpha，但整体结构
length over here of this takes the place
of the B alpha but the overall structure
这个方程的结构因子的
of that of the of the structure factor
here of this equation stays pretty much
相同的唯一区别是原子形状因子也是
the same the only difference is the
atomic form factor is also a function of
阶梯的倒数晶格矢量G，而在这里不是
the of the ladder the reciprocal lattice
vector G whereas over here it's not and
之所以不在这里是因为我们有一个很好的简单Delta函数
the reason it's not over here is because
we have a nice simple Delta function
在这里进行互动，如果您在这里进行更复杂的互动
interaction over here and we have a more
complicated interaction over here if you
想知道G的f的实际形式，实际上是整数d3r
want to know the actual form of f of G
it's actually an integral d3r it's just
我想也许萨瓦尔（Salal）提出了傅立叶变换gr t sub-alpha
the Fourier transform
gr t sub-alpha I guess maybe Saval put
首先是z子alpha，然后是我们的G子alpha，所以它只是傅立叶
the z sub-alpha first then G sub alpha
of our so it's just the Fourier
形状函数G的变换也许是这个积分是
transform of the shape function G the
surprise maybe is this integral is
实际上不仅在晶胞上，而且在整个空间上，我都不会
actually over all space not just over
the unit cell and that I'm not going to
经过整个推导，我认为有一个修订作业
go through the whole derivation I think
there's a revision homework assignment
要求您尝试解决它，也许是去年，也许是
that asks you to try to work through it
maybe or there was last year maybe it's
今年不存在，但是值得尝试，因为它在书中
not there this year but it's worth
trying to do it's it's it's in the book
但是请尝试说服您积分应该是整体空间，然后让
but the to try to convince you that the
integral should be overall space and let
我提出以下论点，所以这些形状函数G的尾巴很长
me make the following argument so these
these shape functions G have long tails
我的意思是，这些尾巴很小，但它们却很长，如果您只是
I mean this tails are small but they but
they go out a long way if you're only
加总晶胞内的原子，您将永远不会感觉到
adding up over atoms within the unit
cell you would never feel the tail of
这些形状函数之一，因为您只累加了
one of those those shape functions
because you're only adding up over
晶胞内的Alpha，但是您应该包括所有的尾巴
alphas within the unit cell what but you
should be including the tails of all
你的邻居，所以那里有亚当斯的出路，其他
your neighbors
so there's Adams way out there and other
单位细胞，那么您应该感觉到那些形状的尾巴
unit cells then you should be feeling
the tails of those of those shape
功能，所以您要整合所有空间的事实是
functions and so the the fact that
you're integrating all over all space is
跟踪G的短距离部分和G的尾部
keeping track of both the short-range
part of G and the tails of the of the
G来自更远的其他原子，所以它们全都吸引了我一些
G's from other atoms farther away so
they all sort of get me some and come
到这里的形状因素中，所以我将不做推导
into the the form factor here okay so
I'm not going to do the derivation it's
可能不值得做，但无论如何可能都是在做些有趣的事
probably not worth doing but
might be where it's doing for fun anyway
该形状因数的形式或多或少看起来像这样，所以我们将绘制F
the the form of this form factor more or
less looks like this so we'll draw F
alpha在这里，对于G等于零，对于G等于零，我们将在此处绘制G
alpha here we'll draw G over here for G
equal to zero for G equals zero equals
零个F sub alpha只是Z sub alpha它基本上只是在计算你可以
zero F sub alpha is just Z sub alpha
it's just basically counting you can
有点看是否在空间G上的那个整数中插入零
kind of see if you insert zero into that
integral over space G is a normalized
形状函数，这样您就可以使Z返回，因此，如果G为零，则可以得到Z sub
shape function so you just get Z back
out so so if G is zero you get Z sub
Alpha在这里，但随后会逐渐衰减到更小
alpha up here but then it sort of decays
slowly down to something much smaller
并且衰变长度在的原子半径范围内或多或少为1
and the decay length is more or less 1
over the radius of the atom radius of
原子经常被人们认为α的F是一个近似值
atom very frequently people just make
the approximation that F of alpha is a
常数，常数就是电子数，因为你知道
constant and the constant is just the
number of electrons because you know if
你有更多的电子，你从原子上散射的更多，所以让我们
you have more electrons you scatter more
off of it off of the atom so just let's
假设形状因子与G无关，并且基本上
assume that the form factor is
independent of G and it's basically just
与G中的电子数成正比，这并不可怕
proportional to the number number of
electrons in G it's not a horrible
近似值并不完全正确，但还算不错，让您的生活更美好
approximation it isn't completely right
but it's not too bad and makes your life
简单得多，它使X射线问题看起来更像
a lot simpler it makes the the x-ray
problem look a lot more like the the
这些B的形状因子不依赖于G的中子问题
neutron problem where these this form
factor this B doesn't depend on G
不再依赖于互易的晶格因子，而是严格地
anymore it doesn't depend on the
reciprocal lattice factor but strictly
讲F应该衰减也是G的函数，所以通常在
speaking F should decay as a function of
G as well so generally where they were
谈论X射线，或者我们谈论中子，总是会有G
talking about x-rays or we're talking
about neutrons will always have s of G
单元格e中的adams alpha adams alpha上以下形式的总和
of the following form sum over adams
alpha adams alpha in unit cell e to the
IG点R alpha，然后我将其写为G的f但或或alpha的野兽
I G dot R alpha and then well I'll write
it as f of G but or or beasts of alpha
如果我们在谈论中子，那么经常重写是很方便的
if we're talking about neutrons
it's convenient frequently to rewrite
就米勒指数而言，因此，如果我们根据
this in terms of Miller indices so if we
rewrite these statements in terms of
米勒指数，我们将在晶胞e中获得超过2 alpha H倍的alpha值
Miller indices we would have some over
alpha in unit cell e to the 2 pi H times
u alpha加K乘以V alpha加L乘以W F为F sub alpha HKL，所以
u alpha plus K times V alpha plus L
times W alpha of F sub alpha H K L so
这里H KL h KL是GG向量和u alpha的Miller指数
here H KL h KL is the Miller indices
Miller indices of G G vector and u alpha
v alpha W alpha等于原子alpha alpha在晶胞中的位置
v alpha W alpha equals position position
of atom alpha alpha in unit cell okay
到目前为止，让人们开心的事让我们实际做一个例子
that make people happy good so far all
right let's actually do an example to
使其中的一些内容更加清晰，因此我们之前讨论过的示例材料
make make some of this more clear so
example material we talked about before
氯化铯，所以您还记得氯化铯是简单立方的
cesium chloride so you remember cesium
chloride is simple cubic with basis with
基，并且基的铯为0 0 0 0 0 0 0，氯为1/2 1/2 1/2
basis and the basis has a cesium at 0 0
0 0 0 0 and a chlorine at 1/2 1/2 1/2
实际上我想我可能对此有一张照片，我希望这看起来
and actually I think I may have a
picture of that yeah I hope this looks
熟悉的我们花了一些时间讨论它
familiar we spent some time discussing
it
因此，使用该表达式作为结构因子，我们可以编写s
so using that expression for the
structure factor we can we can write s
在香港，l等于好，所以它将是单元中两个原子的总和
at HK l equals okay so it's going to be
a sum over the two atoms in the unit
单元格，因此第一个原子位于0 0 0，因此e
cell
so the first atom is at 0 0 0 so e to
2 pi然后我们在楼上有一堆零，所以第一个项将是
the 2 pi then we have a bunch of zeros
upstairs so the first term will just be
F铯，因为e到2 pi 0只会给你一个好处，这
F cesium because e to the 2 pi 0 is just
going to give you one good and this
我们将F氯乘以e到2 pi，然后将h乘以1/2加K
we'll be F chlorine times e to the 2 pi
and then we have h times 1/2 plus K
乘以1/2加L乘以1/2可以堵住氯气的位置
times 1/2 plus L times 1/2
ok plugging in the position of chlorine
UV和W均为氯的1/2现在我可以将其重写为FC并严格
UV and W both being 1/2 for chlorine now
I can rewrite that as FC and strictly
严格来说，我应该给铯中的F和HKL中的F氯
speaking strictly speaking I should have
given F at cesium and F chlorine HKL
我刚在那边大声疾呼的依赖，所以他们严格来说
dependencies as I just ranted about up
there so they're strictly speaking there
也是h KL的功能h KL的弱功能也取决于
are also functions of h KL weak
functions of h KL as well they depend
关于G的大小，但我通常不会写那个
slightly on on the magnitude of G but I
typically won't write that write that
依赖性，但您必须记住它确实存在，因此我们可以重写
dependence but you have to remember that
it's actually there so we can rewrite
作为这里的铯，为了方便起见，我将不再依赖HK L
that as f cesium in here I'm gonna drop
the dependence on HK L for convenience
乘以F clora加上F氯，然后将此e乘以2 pi H乘以1/2加上
times F clora plus F chlorine and this
factor of e to the 2 pi H times 1/2 plus
想要拥有的K倍1/2加L倍实际上是h减去1/2加k加L
K times 1/2 plus L times want to have is
actually minus 1/2 the h plus k plus L
很好，所以这是结构因素，您把这个东西平方即可得到
good so this is the structure factor and
you square this thing this will give you
20的平方，它将使您的散射幅度为2o，K为负
the 20 squared it will give you the
amplitude of scattering 2o with K minus
米勒指数给出的K素数HK L好吧，让我们再举一个例子
K prime given by Miller indices HK L
okay all right let's do another example
举例来说，纯铯旁边的两个是铯，现在您还记得那是BCC
example two next to pure cesium here are
cesium now you remember that that's BCC
但BCC可以被认为是简单的三次方，其基础是
but BCC can be thought of as simple
cubic with a basis with basis where the
铯是0 0 0，铯是1/2 1/2 1/2，换句话说，我们只是
basis is cesium at 0 0 0 and cesium at
1/2 1/2 1/2 so in other words we're just
我们之前已经讨论过用另一种铯代替氯，所以有
replacing the chlorine by another cesium
we discussed this before and so there's
它的图片，所以您只需用铯代替氯即可，
a picture of it so you just replace the
chlorine with a cesium so we get exactly
相同的结果，但现在是f氯，这是来自中心的氯
the same result except now f chlorine
and this is the chlorine from the center
的单位电池与f铯相同，所以现在我们将
of the unit cell it's
to be the same as f cesium so now we'll
得到s HK l等于f铯+ f铯x-1直至h加k加L，我们
get s HK l equals f cesium + f cesium x
- 1 up to the h plus k plus L and we
想要我们可以分解出铯，并将铯乘以1加负1
want to we can factor out the F cesium
and write f cesium times 1 plus minus 1
h加k加L现在，您会注意到它消失了，除非写下
the h plus k plus L now you'll notice
that this vanishes unless write this
下降消失，更少的h加k加L等于H加k加L等于
down vanishes and less h plus k plus L
is even H plus k plus L is even this is
所谓的选择规则或系统性缺席，也许我会写
what's known as a selection rule or a
systematic absence maybe I'll write
那些选择不足的人将统治或系统性缺席系统性缺席
those down selection will rule or
systematic absence systematic absence
缺席感系系统性缺席
absence absence sense systematic absence
um the idea being that you will get no
除非h加k加L都是偶数，否则所有具有h的米勒指数
scattering unless h plus k plus L is
even so all of the Miller indices with h
加k加al为奇数根本没有散射
plus k plus al being odd have no
scattering at all they are
有序地从散射或其他方式来
systematically absent from this from the
scattering or another way words in order
为了得到散射，您必须满足此选择规则，这通常是
to get scattering you must satisfy this
selection rule and this is generally
对于BCC晶格为true对于BCC晶格对于BCC晶格，这些是选择
true for BCC lattices for BCC lattices
for BCC lattices these are the selection
现在就规则了，所以每当您进行分散实验时，如果发现
rules now so whenever you do a
scattering experiment if you discover
这些米向量的所有米勒指数都由H加k加
that all the Miller indices scattering
by these wave vectors with H plus k plus
如果发现h加k加L的奇数没有
L not any time if you discover that h
plus k plus L odd that there's no
在那些米勒指数处将其散射，但您确实发现了h的散射
scattering it there at those Miller
indices but you do find scattering for h
加k加L甚至很好地打赌您拥有的是BCC晶格
plus k plus L even it's a very very good
bet that what you have is a BCC lattice
但是你会被愚弄你怎么会被愚弄你会被愚弄
however you can be fooled how can you be
fooled you can be fooled
例如，让我们考虑一下氯化铯的情况
for example let's consider the case of
cesium chloride suppose just
巧合的是铯和氟氯在某种程度上彼此相等
coincidentally F cesium and F chlorine
we're equal to each other by some
巧合的是，在这种情况下，您将在这里消失得一样
coincidence in which case you'd get the
same vanishing over here you'd have the
相同的选择角色，但是如果它们不同，则可能
same selection role but if they're
different maybe by a little bit then the
选择规则几乎可以满足，这意味着您必须看起来很真实
selection rule is almost satisfied
meaning that you'd have to look really
真的很认真地看到有一些振幅，因为这些会
really carefully to see that there was
some amplitude because these would
几乎完全取消，所以抓住氯化物不具有此特性F
almost exactly cancel so seizing
chloride does not have this property F
铯和F氯不是很相似，但是有非常相似的
cesium and F chlorine are not very
similar but there's a very very similar
这两个材料非常接近的材料，您可能会
material for which these two are
extremely close and you might be
如果您查看数据，可能会误会，并且可能会出错，除非
mistaken you might if you looked at the
data you might make a mistake and unless
你仔细地看了一下，就会以为
you looked at it really carefully you
would think that you would have the same
任何人都想猜出该物质是什么氯化钾的选择规则
selection rule anyone want to guess what
that material is what potassium chloride
你以为你是谁说过的话我还是会给你的
who do you think you said that way up
there I'll give this to you anyway but
这不是正确的答案氯化钾是一个很好的猜测
it's not the right answer
potassium chloride is a very good guess
而之所以认为和氯化物是一个很好的猜测是因为
and the reason the reason for that and
chloride is a good guess is because
请记住，这些F这些形状因子基本上与原子成正比
remember that these F these form factors
are basically proportional to the atomic
铯和氯的原子数和原子数有很大不同
number and the atomic number of cesium
and chlorine are extremely different
氯是什么氯氯是17号而铯是55号
chlorine is what is chlorine chlorine is
number 17 and cesium is number number 55
因此这两个数字将有很大的不同，但是如果您替换了
so these two numbers will be extremely
different but if you replaced the
氯铯与钾钾在上方
chlorine the cesium with potassium
potassium is right above it on the
周期表在化学上非常相似，然后看到钾具有原子
periodic table it's chemically very
similar then see potassium has atomic
19号和氯原子序号为17，所以这些原子数是多余的，
number 19 and chlorine has the atomic
number 17 so these would be extra and
您几乎要取消氯化钾是不正确的答案，因为
you'd have a near cancellation potassium
chloride is not the right answer because
实际上，氯化钾并不具有这种晶体结构，它需要
in fact potassium chloride does not take
this crystal structure and it takes a
不同的晶体结构是FCC，就像是氯化钠，是FCC
different crystal structure is FCC it's
like it's like sodium chloride it's FCC
在此基础上还有另一种材料，但这暗示着其他
with the basis there's another material
but that's a hint what's the other
更像氯化铯的物质
material that would be more like cesium
chloride
不，不，镁，不，不，我要自己保留这个，这是一些
no not magnesium no no all right I'm
gonna keep this one myself it's some
碘化铯，如果用2 2个空格的碘代替氯
caesium iodide if you replace chlorine
with iodine which is which is 2 2 spaces
在它的周期表下，碘的原子序数为53和铯
under it on the periodic table the
iodine has atomic number 53 and caesium
原子序数为55，因此这两者之间的取消为
has atomic number 55 so the cancellation
between these two would be
几乎完全正确，我的意思是您只需要几个百分点
almost exact I mean only within a few
percent you would you would have a
轻微的非取消，因此您很容易犯错误并查看
slight non cancellation so you it's very
easy to make the mistake and look at the
数据，并认为您拥有密件抄送格，因为您认为
data and think that you have a BCC
lattice because you think there's a
全身性的缺失，但是如果仔细观察，就会发现
systemic absence but if you look at it
much much more closely you discover that
事实上，这并不能完美消除所有人的快乐，好吧，好吧
in fact it's not perfectly canceling
okay everyone happy all right so right
考虑到FCC FCC的情况，我们可以对FCC格做同样的事情
we can do the same thing with with FCC
lattices considering a case of FCC FCC
晶格，所以对于FCC，我们可以认为FCC等于基本简单立方时间
简单的三次方，偶然的基础，我应该有
basis simple cubic times the basis
incidentally um I should I should have
提到这一点，如果我们正在研究核散射长度，那么有
mentioned this if we were looking at
nuclear scattering lengths then there's
绝对没有理由您应该期望任何两个都一样
absolutely no reason you should ever
expect any two would be the same
与他们的原子序数无关，因为我的意思是你可以拥有一个
氢的散射长度恰好发生在一个奇怪的巧合
strange coincidence that the scattering
lengths of hydrogen happens to happen to
匹配铁的散射长度或类似的疯狂东西，但
match the scattering length of iron or
something crazy like that but just
因为它们在元素周期表中彼此靠近并不意味着
because they're close to each other in
the periodic table doesn't mean that
他们有紧密的核散射长度，完全不相关，所以
they have close nuclear scattering
lengths completely unrelated so it's
如果您认为几乎可以取消使用X射线，那有时会很好
sometimes good if you think there's a
near cancellation to switch from x-rays
到中子，因为X射线几乎不会抵消
to neutrons because a near cancellation
with x-rays won't be in near
用中子消除通常可以回到FCC FCC，我们可以认为
cancellation with neutrons generally all
right back to FCC FCC and we can think
它是简单的三次方，其底基等于底基等于0 0 0 0
of it as simple cubic with a basis where
the basis equals basis equals 0 0 0 0
和1/2 1/2 0 1/2 0 1/2和0 1/2 1/2实际上我想我有一张
and 1/2 1/2 0 1/2 0 1/2 and 0 1/2 1/2
actually I think I have a picture of
还要记住，从FCC的一些演讲之前，这是
that as well remember this from from a
couple lectures ago the FCC lattice is
可以穿透简单的三次方，所以我们可以写出结构因子
for interpenetrating simple cubics okay
so we can write the structure factor the
结构因子将是这四个四个晶格点的总和
structure factor is going to be the sum
over all these four four lattice points
在e到2 pi和i'的常规单位格内
within the conventional unit cell of e
to the 2 pi and i'll
这个HKL点到UV W点alpha中，我们可以写成1加e到
this HKL dotted into UV W point alpha
which we can then write as 1 plus e to
I pi h加，所以一个是从0 0 0，那么我将得到h加k加e
the I pi h plus so one is from 0 0 0
then we'll have h plus k plus e to the I
pi H加L加e至I pi k加L，然后等于1加-1至
pi H plus L plus e to the I pi k plus L
which is then equal to 1 plus -1 to the
h加k加-1到h加L加1减去k加L然后我声称
h plus k plus -1 to the h plus L plus
minus 1 the k plus L then I claim that
除非HK l HK L全部为偶数或全部为奇数，并且使您信服，
this vanishes unless HK l HK L all even
or all odd and to convince you of that
如果HK和L都是偶数，那么所有这些指数集都是偶数，所以它是1
if HK and L are all even then all those
sets of exponents are even so it's 1
加1加1加1，如果HK和L均为奇数，则再加到加在一起的几率
plus 1 plus 1 plus 1 if HK and L are all
odd then again to odds added together
总是给你一个偶数，所以它又是1加1加1加1但如果你有
always give you an even so it's again 1
plus 1 plus 1 plus 1 but if you have for
例如，一个奇数和两个偶数让我们考虑一下这种情况，假设H为
example one odd and two evens let's
think about that case let's suppose H is
奇数，并且K和L或什至然后H加K为奇数h加上L为奇数，但k加L为偶数
odd and K and L or even then H plus K is
odd h plus L is odd but k plus L is even
所以我们将有1减1减1加1并消失，您可以说服
so we'll have 1 minus 1 minus 1 plus 1
and vanishes and you can convince
你自己，除非HK和L全都是奇数
yourself that unless HK and L are either
all even are all odd
您会消失的，所以这是FCC的选择规则，所以在哪里
you'll get your vanish so this is a
selection rule rule for for FCC so where
如果您还记得的话，请执行这些选择规则实际来自的地方
do these where these selection rules
actually come from if you remember back
到上一讲或我们讨论晶格族之前的讲课
to the last lecture or the lecture
before we discussed families of lattice
平面以及米勒指数的某些集合与
planes and how it is that certain sets
of Miller indices do not correspond to
BCC和FCC晶格的晶格平面族，因此请记住例如
families of lattice planes for BCC and
FCC lattices so remember for example
1 0 0晶格平面族或倒数晶格向量对应于
with 1 0 0 family of lattice planes or
reciprocal lattice vector corresponds to
这些这些平面的简单立方
this these sets of planes for simple
cubic
如果我尝试将一个零零用于BCC，那将不是最后一个家庭
if I tried to use that one zero zero for
BCC it would not be a family of last
飞机，因为您会想念常规中心的家伙
planes because you would miss the the
guy in the center of the conventional
晶胞必须上升到两个零零才能获得第二好的
unit cell you have to go up to two zero
zero in order to get that second best
中间的额外平面的平面间距较小，以便抓住
the extra plane in the middle a smaller
plane spacing in order to catch that
常规晶胞中间的附加晶格点
additional additional lattice point in
the middle of the conventional unit cell
好吧伙计，这听起来很熟悉吗，我希望如此
okay dude is this sound familiar vaguely
familiar I hope so
现在这就是为什么2 0 0满足BCC选择规则，而1 0 0一打
now this is why 2 0 0 satisfies the BCC
selection rule whereas 1 0 0 a dozen for
密件抄送的选择规则是h加k加L应为2
BCC the selection rule is that h plus k
plus L should be even that is true for 2
0 0这不是选择规则的起源1 0 0
0 0 it is not true for 1 0 0 that's the
origin of the selection rule the
选择规则询问这组已知索引实际上何时
selection rule is asking when is this
set of known indices actually a
此特定晶格的倒数晶格矢量
reciprocal lattice vector for this
particular lattice that's where it's
来自您可以看到另一种情况1 1 1 1 1 1使这些对角线
coming from you can see another case
with 1 1 1 1 1 1 makes these diagonal
飞机在这里横穿单位晶胞，但如果
planes here cutting across the unit cell
here but it would miss the BCC point if
我们在考虑BCC时，我们会错过
we was thinking about BCC we'd be
missing the point in the center of the
单位晶格，如果去2 2 2则具有两倍于
unit cell if you went to 2 2 2 you have
twice the density of lattice plane of
飞机在这里，您将捕捉到单元中心的晶格点
planes here and you would catch the
lattice point in the center of the unit
单元1 1 1不满足B加选择规则，即h加k加L
cell 1 1 1 does not satisfy the BCC
selection rule that h plus k plus L
应该是偶数，而2 2 2可以，所以这就是当你有一个
should be even whereas 2 2 2 does okay
so that's how you tell when you have a
真正的接收者温迪·米勒（Wendy Miller）指数实际上代表一个倒数晶格
real recipient Wendy Miller indices
actually represent a reciprocal lattice
向量，当它们满足
vector they represent a reciprocal
lattice vector when they satisfy the
选择角色，当它们出现时，它们不代表倒易的晶格向量
selection role and they do not represent
a reciprocal lattice vector when they do
不能代表它满足选择角色，好吧，是的，很好
not represent it satisfy the selection
role okay make sense yeah good all right
关于这些选择规则，这些方面真的很酷的一件事是
one thing that's really cool about these
about these selection rules is that in
事实上，当您可以描述任何晶体时，我们可以将晶体描述为晶格
fact when you can describe any crystal
we can describe a crystal as a lattice
这十四种晶格类型中的任何一种乘以基数，这是其中之一
any one of these fourteen lattice types
times a basis this is one of the things
我们检查了晶体结构，例如氯化钠
we went over we did crystal structure
for example sodium chloride
这是FCC晶格，然后乘以一个基础，告诉您有钠
it's an FCC lattice but then times a
basis which tells you there's a sodium
为零零零，氯为1/2 1 1/2 1/2时，选择规则仍为
is zero zero zero and a chlorine at 1/2
1 1/2 1/2 the selection rules remain the
相同于倾向于选择规则的规则
same in
tend to the basis selection rules rules
在基础上是独立的，因此有助记符
are independent independent in depth of
basis so there's a mnemonic for how it
是人们记得这一点吗？经常说s是s
is that people remember this it's
frequently said that s is s for the
晶格乘以s为基础，因此如果s的晶格消失，则整个
lattice times s for the basis so if s
for the lattice vanishes then the whole
事情消失了，所以让我们看看是否可以放一些您知道的方程式
thing vanishes ok so let's see if we can
put some you know some equations behind
我的意思是s为晶格乘以s为基础，所以让我们
this what I mean by s for the lattice
times s for the basis all right so let's
回想一下，s将是亚当斯alpha和f sub alpha的晶胞的总和
recall that s is going to be a sum over
adams alpha and unit cell of f sub alpha
e到i g-- r alpha然后我们可以用a来写任何原子alpha
e to the i g-- r alpha and then we can
write any atom alpha in terms of a
晶格点和基向量x，所以这是晶格点大R
lattice point and a basis vector x so
this is lattice point big R that point
X是基向量基，因此它的位置R alpha是
and X is the basis vector basis so that
its position R alpha is the position of
该原子的晶格矢量R和该原子的基矢量X
the lattice vector R for that atom and
the basis vector X for that atom so for
例如，钠的X为0，它正好位于晶格上
example X for sodium here is 0 it's
sitting right on the lattice where X for
氯是1/2 1/2 1/2这告诉你要找出一个氯的位置
chlorine is 1/2 1/2 1/2 which tells you
that you take to find the position of a
氯到达晶格点，然后将其放在向量X处
chlorine you go to a lattice point and
then you just place it by a vector X for
氯是1/2 1/2 1/2所以我只是写原子的坐标
chlorine which is 1/2 1/2 1/2 so I'm
just writing the coordinates of the atom
就其晶格坐标和基础位移而言，可以
in terms of its lattice coordinate and
the basis displacement okay all right so
那么我们就可以这样写s为R上的和X上的和
then we can write s in terms of this as
sum over R in lattice sum over X in
基于F的形式因数仅取决于X，因此它仅取决于X
basis of F the form factor is only going
to depend on X because it only cares
您正在谈论的原子类型是钠还是氯，所以
what type of atom you're talking about
whether it's a sodium or a chlorine so f
这里只取决于X乘以e到I G，然后位置R小R大
only depends on X here times e to the I
G and then the position R small R is big
R加上大R加上大X好的，那么我们可以将其写为
R plus big R plus big X
okay then we can factor this write it as
等于R在晶格时间e中的和与I GE R在X和基数上的和
equal to sum over R in lattice times e
to the I GE R times sum over X and basis
在F sub X e到IG点X的基础上，所以这就是我们上面计算的
in basis F sub X e to the I G dot X okay
so this is what we just calculated above
这是s的格子，这是s的基础，所以真的很漂亮
this is s for the lattice and this here
is s for the basis so it's really pretty
严格说来，任何晶体的结构因素就是结构
much strictly true that the structure
factor for any crystal is the structure
晶格系数乘以结构系数
factor for the lattice alone times the
structure factor this factor here for
基础，因此如果晶格的结构因子消失，换句话说，如果
the basis so if the structure factor for
the lattice vanishes in other words if
您不满足晶格类型的选择规则，则
you're not satisfying the selection rule
for the for the lattice type then the
整个事情都会消失，所以无论您的复杂程度如何
whole thing is going to vanish so it
doesn't matter how complicated your
基础是如果是FCC为了获得散射，您必须满足FCC
basis is if it's FCC in order to get
scattering you have to satisfy the FCC
HK和L的散布规则必须全部为偶数或全部为奇数行，现在有一个
scattering rules in H K and L have to be
all even or all odd okay now there's a
解释您必须满足选择的陈述的方式
way to interpret this statement that
that you have to satisfy the selection
规则仅用于晶格，以便从复杂的物体中散射
rule for the lattice alone in order to
get scattering from a complicated
晶体，所以让我们考虑一下这张图片，用氯化钠
crystal so let's think about this
picture here with sodium chloride for a
再想一秒钟，我们忽略了氯，只是摆脱了
second imagine for a second that we
ignore the chlorines just get rid of the
氯，然后剩下的就是FCC晶格上的钠，以便
chlorines and then what we have left is
sodium's on an FCC lattice in order to
从那些钠中得到X射线散射或中子散射
get x-ray scattering or neutron
scattering from those sodium's you have
满足选择规则，否则您将不会从中分散
to satisfy the selection rule otherwise
you get no scattering from it now let's
摆脱钠是，并把氯中的氯也
get rid of the sodium is and put the
chlorines in the chlorines are also
形成一个完整的FCC晶格，以便从
forming a complete FCC lattice and in
order to get scattering from the
如果您放回氯气，现在必须满足选择规则
chlorines you have to satisfy the
selection rule now if you put them back
都通过叠加返回，这将是两者的总和
both back in by superposition in order
it's just going to be the sum of the two
从钠和苏纳特和
scatterings the scatterings from the
sodium's and the sunnat' and the
从氯中飞散出来，所以如果您不满足选择规则
scattering from the chlorines so if
you're not satisfying the selection rule
对于其中之一，您不是，所以您根本不会得到任何散射，所以
for one of them you're not so you're not
gonna get any scattering at all so it's
基本上只是说您将各个部分的散射加起来
basically just saying that you add up
the scattering from each of the pieces
分别好吧，好了，所以在下一个讲座中我们要去
separately okay all right
so in the next lecture what we're going
我们要做的是，我们将实际查看一些真实的X射线数据
to do is we're going to yeah we're going
to actually look at some real x-ray data
然后我们将分析X射线数据并推论出什么是真实的
and we're going to analyze the x-ray
data and deduce what is in some real
材料，但其中之一应该知道
materials but one of the things that
were expected to know that sort of has
首先要讨论的是如何制作X射线
to be discussed is how you make x-rays
in the first place how to make make
X射线，所以有两种制作X射线的方法，我们可能只能获得X射线
x-rays so there's two ways to make
x-rays which we may only be able to get
到今天最简单的方式，但最简单的方式又便宜又简单
to the simplest of them today but the
simple way the cheap way simple and
便宜的是使用X射线管X射线管，这是Ron Chen发现的方法
cheap is to use an x-ray tube x-ray tube
this is a method discovered by Ron Chen
追溯到1919年1900年1901年，您的想法是
way back in you know around 1919 1900
1901 the idea is you take a great big
此处的电压，您将其放在阴极的这一侧
voltage here and you put it across a
cathode on this side just a piece of
这边的金属和这边的大目标
metal on this side and a big target on
this side target on this side and by
拥有如此巨大的电压，您会将电子从阴极吐出，
having this huge voltage
you spit electrons off the cathode and
电子击中目标并发出X射线，所以真正发生了什么
the electrons hit the target and off
come x-rays so what's really happening
这是电子快电子快速电子被踢出
here is that the electrons fast
electrons fast electrons kick out
来自核心轨道的电子将来自核心轨道的电子踢出
electrons from core orbitals kick out
electrons from core orbitals from core
而您看到的X射线主要来自其他
and the x-rays you see the x-ray lines
you actually see are mainly from other
电子从高轨道下降到核心的外观
electrons falling down from the high
orbitals down to the look to the core
轨道重新填充它们，因此请参见发射
orbitals to refill them so see emission
来自电子跃迁的跃迁，因此高电子跃迁
from transitions from electron
transitions so an electron in a high up
轨道下降以填充核心轨道中的这些空白区域之一
orbital drops down to fill one of these
empty spaces in the in the core orbitals
然后您会看到一条漂亮的X射线线进入了一条漂亮的X射线，现在能量
and you'll see a nice x-ray line come in
a nice x-ray coming off now the energy
过渡的时间基本上是里德伯格乘以原子
of that of that transition is basically
about the rid berg times the atomic
数字平方记得当你有一个氢原子的能量时
number squared remember when you have a
hydrogen atom the energy of the the
氢原子的本征态随核电荷的平方而变化，所以你知道
eigenstates of the hydrogen atom go as
the nuclear charge squared so you know
红鸟是13电子伏特，但如果您是
the Redbird is 13 electron volts but the
atomic number of your atom if you're
用铜之类的东西40之类的东西
using something like copper something
like 40 so you can have a huge huge
能量可以是几十千伏的ke v，并且将非常对应
energy this can be tens of kilovolts of
ke v and that will correspond very
恰好与我们想要的对应于我们想要的lambda
nicely to what we want correspond to
what we want which is lambda
现在大约有一个埃
approximately one angstrom now there's a
couple of really nice things about this
这项技术真正很棒的一件事是，因为它是一种
technique one thing that's really nice
about this technique is since it's an
原子过渡，这非常非常尖锐。
atomic transition it's very very sharp
in other words bits it's a very sharp
在两个不同的能级之间建立非常非常独特的过渡
line a very very distinct transition
between two distinct energy levels you
知道这里很清楚的能量水平那里很清楚的能量水平
know very clear energy level up here a
very clear energy level down there and
因此，您可以从中获得非常明确的定义明确的lambda
so you get a very very well-defined
well-defined defined lambda out of this
类型的技术，这基本上就是罗恩·陈所做的
type of technique and this is basically
what what Ron Chen was doing you know
100 115年前的现在，在现代的现代时代，我可能有也可能没有
100 115 years ago now in modern in the
modern era I may or may not have a
这幅画让我看看我是否拥有它是在现代时代
picture of this let me see if I have it
yeah here in the modern era there's
另一种制作X射线的方法是一种更好的技术，
another way to make x-rays which is sort
of favored as a better technique is only
这些X射线管非常便宜
these x-ray tubes they're they're
incredibly cheap
你能知道这是你在牙医诊所里所拥有的
you can you know this is what you have
in the doctor the dentist office when
口腔X射线就是其中之一，或者您知道X射线断了骨头
the x-ray your mouth is one of these
things or you know x-ray broken bones
这些就是这些东西，您可以在这座建筑物周围找到许多
it's these things and there's probably
dozen them around this building you can
如果愿意，可以自己建一个，但如果经常，则需要更多
build one yourself if you wanted to but
if frequently you need a much more
高科技X射线源和现代高科技X射线源被称为
high-tech x-ray source and the modern
high-tech x-ray source is known as the
同步加速器叉，在这张照片中，这是这些大建筑物之一
synchrotron prong and it's in this
picture it's one of these big buildings
这就是即将发生的事情这是钻石实验室的X射线同步加速器源
this is just down the road this is the
x-ray synchrotron source at Diamond Lab
就在路上，开车约十分钟，这些东西大概是十
just just up the road by about ten
minutes by car these things are about 10
到10倍亮10到10是10到10倍亮
to the 10th times brighter 10 to the 10
yeah 10 to the 10 times brighter more
光子，然后是X射线管，然后是X射线管，这实际上非常有用
photons then x-ray tubes then x-ray
tubes and that's actually quite useful
如果有很多现代实验来检验
to have if for a lot of modern
experiments which examine either
非常小的样本，或者您需要非常快速地收集数据，我的意思是
extremely small samples or you need to
collect data extremely quickly I mean at
一天结束时，您总是在计数光子
the end of the day you're always
counting photons you're sort of counting
如果有更多光子，则在特定方向上会散布多少光子
how many photons are scattered in
particular direction if you have more
光子特别是如果您总是会得到更好的数据
photons you always get better data if
you're if it's particularly if you're
看着很小的样品，很难将这些电子聚焦在
looking at a very small sample where
it's hard to focus those electrons in on
小样本同步加速器的总体思路是，您将这个伟大
the the small sample the general idea of
the synchrotron is you take this great
大环，您可以在这张照片中看到您旋转的同步加速器源
big ring which you can see in this
picture this synchrotron source you spin
电子围绕这个环，所以电子在这个环周围
electrons around this ring so the
electrons are going around this ring at
在GeV上非常高的速度，所以千兆电子伏特然后
very high velocities at up a GeV
so Giga electron volts and then in order
要从中取出X射线，您需要先带走电子，然后再将其发送通过
to get x-rays out of it you take your
electrons and then you send them through
一堆磁铁，所以南北南北北南南这就是所谓的
a bunch of magnets so north south south
north north south this is known as an
有时是起伏器或摇摆器，其想法是电子通过
undulator or a wiggler sometimes and the
idea is that the electrons going through
他们正在经历非常快，而你让他们通过
this they're going through very fast and
you make them accelerate through and as
你知道加速电子会在这种情况下发出辐射
you know accelerating electrons emits
radiation in this case they will emit
定向准直的X射线辐射
directed x-ray radiation which is
extremely collimated
频率定义非常明确，如果您对某种
extremely well defined frequency and if
you're not happy with the sort of a
技术，这是很重要的，要知道您是否不满意
technique this is sort of important to
know if you're not happy with how well
定义频率是如果您想指定说话并更精确地看到
defined the frequency is if you want to
specify a speak and see more precisely
更精确地指定波长您所做的是衍射已知光
specify a wavelength more precisely what
you do is you diffract off a known
晶体衍射以特定角度从已知晶体中分离出来，
crystal diffract tract off known crystal
crystal at a particular angle and that
将会挑选出您现在感兴趣的特定波长
will pick out a particular wavelength
that you're interested in using now
每当您这样做时，您都会丢弃很多很多
whenever you're doing this you're
throwing away lots and lots and lots of
拥有的光子，但是如果有十到十倍的光子
the photons that you have but if you
have ten to the ten times the number of
首先需要的光子可以扔掉很多，然后您可以
photons that you need to begin with you
can throw away a ton of them and you can
多次衍射以真正指定该波长
diffract multiple times to really
specify that wavelength extremely
精确地进行非常高精度的测量，是的，我认为
precisely and do extremely high
precision measurements yeah I think
这就是我要说的，明天明天见
that's all I have to say about this I
see you tomorrow tomorrow
您
you